<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="DSI_IDL_Specification">
  <title>Interface Description Language (IDL)</title>

  <section>
     

    <title>Overview</title>

     This chapter describes the DSI IDL covering: 

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>the IDL specification</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>an overview of the DSI IDL editor</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>an overview of the code generation</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

     
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Formal interfaces</title>

    <para>One of the more powerful modern programming patterns that has arisen
    in the last years is the concept of formalized interfaces. These formalized
    interfaces have two essential properties:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>They support transparent communication across thread and process
        boundaries – in some cases even across hardware boundaries.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>They provide a formal separation of interface and implementation.
        In an application a formally defined interface may exist more than once
        and each instance could be an encapsulation of a different
        implementation.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The applications based on DSI use formal interfaces described in an
    XML based language.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Service interface inspired by the <acronym>CORBA</acronym>
      model</title>

      <para>The service interface is an implementation of a very small
      <glossterm>CORBA</glossterm> subset, suitable for use in resource-poor
      embedded systems - a sort of "poor man's <acronym>CORBA</acronym>".
      Specifically, it provides the ability to define a formal definition for a
      programming interface. This characterization is valuable because it
      provides an immediate feel for the role that the service interface
      plays.</para>

      <para>A dedicated code generator is used within the build process to
      create proxy and stub objects for all defined service interfaces.</para>

      <para>A client that wishes to make use of a service interface may create a
      proxy object. A server that provides an implementation of a service
      interface must inherit from the stub class in an OO programming language
      (e.g. C++) or register callbacks to the stub in a procedural programming
      language, in C.</para>

      <para>For further details regarding code generation please see the
      appropriate chapter.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The DSI IDL concepts</title>

      <para>Before going to describe the XML syntax of the DSI IDL in detail the
      main concepts will be presented: data types, methods to exchange data
      types and error handling.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Data types</title>

        <para>An <glossterm>API</glossterm> will need the possibility to
        describe information to be transferred between applications. The DSI IDL
        is similar with other static languages where the structure of the
        information is known at compile time and provides a set of primitive
        data types and the possibility to aggregate the primitive data types in
        more complex structures.</para>

        <para>Because out of the interface IDL definition code in a standard
        programming language will be generated the data types are strongly
        oriented at the C++ programming language way of handling data
        types.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Primitive data types</title>

          <para>For an IPC mechanism it is important to define the byte order or
          the alignment. However, on the logical level, in the IDL these facts
          are not important but only the size of the data type is important
          because it defines how much information can be transmitted. The byte
          order and alignment can be freely chosen by the IPC transporting the
          data.</para>

          <section>
            <title>Integer Data Types</title>

            <para>The integer types literals can be used as in C++ accepting the
            same syntax, e.g. using the decimal, octal, hexadecimal base
            notation.</para>

            <table>
              <title>Size for integer data types</title>

              <tgroup cols="2">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis></entry>

                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Size [bytes]</emphasis></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>byte/char</entry>

                    <entry>1</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>signed/unsigned short</entry>

                    <entry>2</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>signed/unsigned int</entry>

                    <entry>4</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>signed/unsigned long long</entry>

                    <entry>8</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Floating Point Types</title>

            <para>As for the integral types, the floating types literals use the
            C++ syntax, e.g. <literal>1.23</literal>, <literal>.23</literal>,
            <literal>1.</literal> , <literal>1.2e10</literal>,
            <literal>2.0f</literal>, etc.</para>

            <table>
              <title>Size for floating point data types</title>

              <tgroup cols="2">
                <tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Type</emphasis></entry>

                    <entry><emphasis role="bold">Size [bytes]</emphasis></entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Float</entry>

                    <entry>4</entry>
                  </row>

                  <row>
                    <entry>Double</entry>

                    <entry>8</entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Boolean Type</title>

            <para>A boolean data type is available and can have as values:
            <literal>true </literal>and <literal>false</literal>.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Enumeration Type</title>

            <para>An enumeration is a data type that can hold a set of values
            specified by the user. Once defined, an enumeration is used very
            much like an integer type.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>String Type</title>

            <para>A string type with dynamic size is available where the content
            is encoded in UTF-8.</para>
          </section>

          <section>
            <title>Buffer Type</title>

            <para>A contiguos region of physical memory storage. A Buffer
            implementation can be different than a Vector of bytes
            implementation, the contiguity is not guranteed for the later
            case.</para>
          </section>
        </section>

        <section>
           

          <title>Compound types</title>

           The compound types can be seen as containers of primitive data types. 

          <section>
            <title>Structure type</title>

            <para>An aggregate of elements of arbitrary types can be used with
            the <literal>Structure</literal> data type. Using this data type
            more complex data types can be built on base of the primitive
            types.</para>
          </section>

           

          <section>
            <title>Vector Type</title>

            <para>An aggregate of elements having the same data type with a
            dynamic size can be used in DSI IDL.</para>
          </section>

           

          <section>
            <title>Variant</title>

            <para>A variant is similar with the <literal>union</literal> data
            type in C++. It is a placeholder to contain just one element from a
            defined set of different data types.</para>
          </section>

           

          <section>
            <title>Map</title>

            <para>A map is a collection of (key,value) pairs where a key appears
            only once in the collection.</para>
          </section>

           
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Exchanging data</title>

        <para>Having possibility to encode information in the available data
        types, the IDL provides also mechanisms to exchange this
        information.</para>

        <section>
          <title>Attributes - interface state information</title>

          <para>Attributes can be used to store state information and are
          different to events or signals which encode stateless information that
          is lost as soon as the signal is emitted. The publish/subscribe
          messaging pattern is provided to the client to retrieve the state
          information. A client will register to the server to be notified on
          changes in the values of the data attributes. When the data changes on
          the server side the client will get the new value of the
          attribute.</para>

          <para>Data attributes and the parameters of request and response
          methods may have any desired type. Both built-in and user-defined
          types may be used but several restrictions apply. One restriction is
          that pointers or references are not supported. If a pointer or
          reference must be transported, it is the responsibility of the
          developer to package it as a data element within some class. He then
          also carries the burden of deciding how this data element can be
          meaningfully transported across an address space boundary.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Informations or events - interface stateless
          information</title>

          <para>Informations in DSI IDL can be used by the server implementing
          an interface to send stateless information or events. The clients can
          notify on available informations to get these events.</para>

          <para>An information can have any number of parameters and also can be
          overloaded, the same information can exist with different signatures
          i.e. accepting different kind of parameters .</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Request methods</title>

          <para>The request methods allow a client to trigger actions on the
          server side. Depending on the underlying IPC mechanism the request
          method can be synchronous (blocking) or asynchronous (non-blocking).
          The DSI IPC protocol provides asynchronous calls.</para>

          <para>A request method can accept any number of parameters. The server
          will process the request and can send back an answer in form of a
          response method.</para>

          <para>Request methods can be overloaded, the same request can exist
          with different signatures i.e. accepting different kind of parameters.
          The designer of the interface can define for the request parameters
          default values which are optional to be provided by the client.</para>

          <para>A request can be coupled to a response or can be of kind "fire
          and forget" with no response. When a request is coupled to a response
          the server must send back the coupled response method.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Response methods</title>

          <para>The response methods can be used by the server as reply to a
          request method.</para>

          <para>A difference to other IDLs is that in DSI other clients than the
          one that has triggered an action on the server over a request can
          notify on all the response methods and can get themselves these
          response. So the other clients can hear all the output traffic a
          server it does.</para>

          <para>Another difference is that a server may send several responses
          as result of a client's request or may send the same response method
          to different request methods.</para>

          <para>A response method, like a request method, can have any number of
          parameters and also can be overloaded.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title>Register methods - server side filters</title>

          <para>Register methods can be seen as a mechanism to apply server side
          filters on the data the server sends to its clients over the
          information methods.</para>

          <para>The server provides parametrized filters and the clients can
          customize these filters. When changes are sent by the server, the
          server will first filter the data and then send it only to the clients
          for which the filter applies. The clients can dynamically
          register/unregister to the server to make use of server
          filters.</para>

          <para>This mechanism was introduced in order to improve performance in
          the system and avoid large traffic of data that will not be used on
          the client side.</para>

          <para>Example:</para>

          <para>Preconditions:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the server can have for the power voltage of the system an
              attribute <varname>voltage</varname> but also an information
              <function>informationVoltage(<parameter>int
              voltage</parameter>)</function></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the server provides for the power voltage information a
              register method, a filter with customizable parameters for the
              voltage conditions: <function>registerVoltageFilter(<parameter>int
              underVoltage</parameter>, <parameter>int
              overVoltage</parameter>)</function></para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>a client monitoring critical voltage conditions is
              interested for under-voltage and over-voltage conditions.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Solutions:</para>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>the client can notify to get permanent updates of the power
              voltage attribute. In this case will get all updates including the
              normal range</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>the client can use the
              <function>registerVoltageFilter</function> with its values and
              will get from the server the
              <function>informationVoltage</function> with the current voltage
              only when the <varname>voltage</varname> is less than
              <parameter>underVotage</parameter> or greater than
              <parameter>overVoltage</parameter> specified values.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Error handling</title>

        <para>Error handling does not have a dedicated support in the DSI IDL.
        Currently it is up to the interface designer to provide responses with
        error codes as parameters indicating if the request was processed
        successfully or not.</para>

        <para>However, the DSI IPC implementation has a dedicated error
        handling.</para>

        <para>For example the attributes can be invalidated from the server
        side, that means the clients will receive special events indicating that
        the attribute value can not be computed currently by the server.</para>

        <para>Other example will be that a server can not process a request as
        it is busy processing the same request from other client. In this case
        the client will get a notification signalling the busy state of the
        server.</para>

        <para>If the interface designer is defining an enumeration with the name
        <function>Error</function> then the code generator will generate an
        additional error handling that can be used on the server side to signal
        a predefined error code and on the client side to get it.</para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>The IDL language</title>

      <para>The DSI IDL is based on XML. Every interface is described in its own
      file and an XML schema is provided to check the validity of the file. The
      XML schema and an Ecore model are provided along with the IDL
      documentation package.</para>

      <para>An example of a DSI IDL interface that covers the main concepts is
      provided too.</para>

      <note>
        <para>It is important to know that the DSI IDL is a subset of another
        IDL used internally by Harman the HBSI (Harman Becker Service
        Interface). The DSI IDL does not use all the features of the HBSI but
        for completion the elements of the HBSI will be mentioned here,
        too.</para>
      </note>

      <para>A common information available for many XML nodes and described only
      for the DSI node is composed from: <literal>Name</literal>,
      <literal>Description</literal>, <literal>Deprecation</literal>,
      <literal>Hint</literal> and <literal>ID</literal>. The
      <literal>ID</literal> is used just to have a faster code generator.</para>

      <section>
        <title>The <literal>DSI</literal> service interface</title>

        <para>The XML node <literal>DSI</literal> contains information regarding
        the service interface like name, version, etc. and containers with
        additional elements available in the interface like data types, methods,
        attributes, etc. The interface information is described below the
        containers are described in the following sections.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Name</literal></title>

          <para>The name of the interface defined in the IDL file. The name will
          identify all implementations of the interface in the service discovery
          directory. Additionally the implementations will set an instance name,
          aka role name, to distinguish from other implementations of the same
          interface.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Description</literal></title>

          <para>Documentation of the interface. This can be used by the
          generator to produce Doxygen documentation directly in the generated
          source code.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Deprecated</literal></title>

          <para>Flag used to inform the interface clients that the interface is
          in a deprecation phase. The interface should not be used
          anymore.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Hint</literal></title>

          <para>In case the interface is marked as deprecated this field can be
          used to provide additional information about the deprecation reason or
          hints about other interface to be used in order to get the same
          functionality.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Extern</literal></title>

          <para>Flag indicating if the data type definitions are all DSI capable
          and can be therefore sent across platforms.</para>

          <para>An application has the possibility to define its own data types
          in non DSI IDL files e.g. in C++ header files, or to use directly the
          <acronym>API</acronym> of a 3rd party software defined in these
          programming language specific files. These data types can be used only
          internally in the application, between different components deployed
          in the application.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Abstract</literal></title>

          <para>Flag to mark if the interface can be used directly or it has to
          be used over a specialization. The concept is similar with abstract
          classes in OO languages.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Version</literal></title>

          <para>The service interfaces have all version numbers in a form
          &lt;major&gt;.&lt;minor&gt;.</para>

          <para>The general rules when defining the version number are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>A change in the major version number (in the first position)
              signifies a change that will break compatibility. This means that
              a method or attribute has been deleted or that the signature of a
              method or attribute has been changed.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>A change in the minor version number (in the second
              position) signifies a change that doesn't break compatibility. An
              example would be when a method or attribute is added.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>Given these rules, deciding if a client of one interface version
          can communicate with the server implementing another version, two
          conditions have to be satisfied:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>The major versions must be identical: MajorVersion(client)
              == MajorVersion(server)</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The minor version of the server must be greater than or
              equal to the minor version of the client: MinorVersion(server)
              &gt;= MinorVersion(client)</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>BaseInterface</literal></title>

          <para>An interface can inherit from other interface - the base
          interface. The current DSI IPC implementation allows only extending of
          enumerations with new ids. No polymorphism is supported for the
          moment.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Includes</literal></title>

          <para>Additional IDL files can be included in the interface. These can
          contain data type definitions.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><literal>DataTypes</literal></title>

        <para>Container with data types defined or included from external files
        in the interface. The container is a sequence of
        <literal>DataType</literal> entries.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>DataType</literal></title>

          <para>The primitive and compund data types supported in DSI IDL are:
          <literal>Boolean</literal>, <literal>Int8</literal>,
          <literal>UInt8</literal>, <literal>Int16</literal>,
          <literal>UInt16</literal>, <literal>Int32</literal>,
          <literal>UInt32</literal>, <literal>Int64</literal>,
          <literal>UInt64</literal>, <literal>Float</literal>,
          <literal>Double</literal>, <literal>String</literal>,
          <literal>Buffer</literal>, <literal>Variant</literal>,
          <literal>Vector</literal>, <literal>Map</literal>.</para>

          <para>A user defined data type has a name and can have, as the
          interface, information about: <literal>Description</literal>,
          <literal>Deprecation</literal>, and <literal>Hint</literal>.</para>

          <para>Additionally the following information can be also provided:
          <literal>Kind</literal>, <literal>Namespace</literal>,
          <literal>Include</literal>, <literal>Container</literal>,
          <literal>Fields</literal> and <literal>BaseType</literal>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Kind</literal></title>

          <para>The kind of a data type can be: <literal>Structure</literal>,
          <literal>Streamable</literal>, <literal>Typedef</literal>.</para>

          <para>A <literal>Structure</literal> data type can be used to define a
          compound data type.</para>

          <para>A <literal>Typedef</literal> data type is an alias for other
          data type.</para>

          <para>A <literal>Streamable</literal> data type is one imported from
          an external non DSI IDL file which has already defined streaming
          operators (not relevant for DSI IDL).</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Namespace</literal></title>

          <para>A data type that is imported in the current interface can be
          available under a <literal>Namespace</literal>.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Include</literal></title>

          <para>The data type is imported from an external file provided by this
          filed.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Container</literal></title>

          <para>The DSI IDL provides some standard containers which are:
          <literal>Vector</literal>, <literal>Variant</literal> and
          <literal>Map</literal>. These were already described in a previous
          section.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Fields</literal></title>

          <para>In case a data type is a compound type the elements of the
          structure are included in a <literal>Fields</literal>
          container.</para>

          <para>Each <literal>Field</literal> XML node can provide information
          about: <literal>Name</literal>, <literal>Description</literal>,
          <literal>Deprecation</literal>, <literal>Hint</literal> and
          <literal>Type</literal>. The type of the filed has to be defined in
          the interface or imported from an external file.</para>

          <para>Additionally, a field can have a default value defined over the
          <literal>DefaultValue</literal> XML node.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
          <title><literal>BaseType</literal></title>

          <para>If the data type is of kind <literal>Typedef</literal>, an
          alias, then the <literal>BaseType</literal> represents the original
          data type name.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><literal>Enums</literal></title>

        <para>This is a container where all the enumerations used by the
        interface are defined.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Enum</literal></title>

          <para>A enumeration has information such: <literal>Name,
          Description</literal>, <literal>Deprecation</literal> and
          <literal>Hint</literal>. The values for the enumeration can be defined
          over the XML node <literal>EnumID</literal>.</para>

          <para>The <literal>EnumID</literal> can also contain information
          about: <literal>Name</literal>, <literal>Description</literal>,
          <literal>Deprecation</literal> and <literal>Hint</literal>.
          Additionally an integer value can be also specified for the
          enumeration id.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><literal>Methods</literal></title>

        <para>The <literal>Methods</literal> container defines all available
        methods of the interface.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Method</literal></title>

          <para>The <literal>Method</literal> XML node contains general
          information about: <literal>Name, Description</literal>,
          <literal>Deprecation</literal> and <literal>Hint</literal>.</para>

          <para>A <literal>Method</literal> can be of type:
          <literal>Request</literal>, <literal>Response</literal>,
          <literal>Information</literal>, <literal>Register</literal> and
          <literal>UnRegister</literal>. All these are explained in the DIS IDL
          concepts section.</para>

          <para>The <literal>Request</literal> methods can be coupled with a
          <literal>Response</literal> method over the XML node
          <literal>Response</literal>.</para>

          <para>The parameters of the method are defined in the
          <literal>Parameters</literal> container.</para>

          <para>Every parameter provides information like: <literal>Name,
          Description</literal>, <literal>Deprecation</literal> and
          <literal>Hint</literal>. A method parameter can have also a default
          value specified over the <literal>DefaultValue</literal> XML node.
          Such a method parameter is optional to be provided by the clients of
          the interface.</para>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><literal>Attributes</literal></title>

        <para>The <literal>Attributes</literal> node is a container for all
        state information provided by the interface.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Attribute</literal></title>

          <para>An attribute is defined by information like: <literal>Name,
          Description</literal>, <literal>Deprecation</literal> and
          <literal>Hint</literal>.</para>

          <para>The <literal>Type</literal> of the attribute refers to a data
          type available in the <literal>DataTypes</literal> container.</para>

          <para>The <literal>Notify</literal> information can be:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para><literal>Always</literal>: the clients will receive the
              value of the attribute every time the server updates it</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>OnChange</literal>: the clients will receive the
              values of the attribute only when the server changes it with a new
              value</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para><literal>Partial</literal>: this applies only for the Vector
              data type. In this case the server can update only a contiguous
              part of the vector. This part can be replaced, deleted or new
              elements added in the vector.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title><literal>Constants</literal></title>

        <para>The <literal>Constants</literal> node is a container for all kind
        of constants defined in the interface.</para>

        <section>
          <title><literal>Constant</literal></title>

          <para>A <literal>Constant</literal> node has among general information
          like: <literal>Name, Description</literal>,
          <literal>Deprecation</literal> and <literal>Hint</literal> also a
          <literal>Type</literal> information and the constant stored in the
          <literal>Value</literal> XML node.</para>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>The service interface editor</title>

    <para>Modifying the XML based definition of a DSI interface is error-prone
    when working directly with the XML content, therefore a dedicated editor is
    used to assist the user in this task. The service interface editor is an
    Eclipse plugin and at HARMAN is integrated together with other Eclipse
    plugins in an IDE, the MoCCA IDE. The plugin assist the user not only on
    modifying the service interface but also in doing additional validation
    tasks, e.g. detecting changes that must be reflected in a service interface
    version change.</para>

    <para>The following figures show some snapshots when working with the
    service interface editor.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Service interface, overview.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/ServiceEditor_Overview.png" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>Service interface, method editor.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/ServiceEditor_Methods.png" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <figure>
      <title>Service interface, types editor.</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="figures/ServiceEditor_Types.png" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title xreflabel="CodeGeneration">Code generation</title>

    <para>The DSI interfaces may be imported and freely used by client
    applications. Support libraries and code generators are provided that allow
    DSI service interfaces to be imported and exported from within:</para>

    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        <para>a Java run-time environment</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a <glossterm>C++</glossterm> environment</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a C environment</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The DSI IPC glue code that brings together the server/client software
    is composed from two parts:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>a DSI library providing an implementation for the DSI IPC
        concepts</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>a code generation part that generates out of the DSI IDL code that
        uses the DSI library and provides abstract concepts, easy to be used by
        the server/client software.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In the following section there will be presented an overview about the
    code generation part.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Service interface as a 'wrapper'</title>

      <para>Every service interface that is defined can be viewed as a 'wrapper'
      around an implementation. The interface provides the formal definition of
      the mechanisms to be used when accessing the implementation. The interface
      mechanism provides a 'stub' class that must be used as the base class from
      which the implementation inherits. It also provides a 'proxy' class that
      can be instantiated in any application. To use the 'wrapped'
      implementation, a client must obtain a proxy. The client only sees the
      proxy, which will in turn ensure that all requests are correctly forwarded
      to the implementation.</para>

      <para>This idea has several consequences. One is that the location of the
      implementation is invisible to the client. The implementation can be in
      the same address space with the client, in other process on the same
      platform (operating system and CPU) or on completely other
      platform.</para>

      <para>In the same way, the service interface provides no information to
      the implementation about the origin of a request (which client and/or how
      many clients in total). Requests from a client are completely anonymous
      from the point of view of the application software.<footnote>
          <para>Of course the source of a request is known within the service
          interface glue code. This is required so that the service interface
          can send the response back to the originator of the request.</para>
        </footnote></para>

      <para>The following figure shows the interaction between the code
      generated out of the DSI IDL service interface and the client/server
      implementation.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Code generation overview for DSI IDL</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="figures/CORBA_Model.bmp" scalefit="1" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The code generation is currently based on the Eclipse JET solution
      for Model-Driven Development (MDD). Further implementations might move to
      the new Eclipse MDD solution Xpand / Xtext.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
